Guide to the Jerrold/Smith Autograph Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Jerrold/Smith autograph collection
1840-1928
GEN MSS 467
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
Letters and other manuscript items representing a wide range of prominent figures in nineteenth century British literature, theater, and art, as well as nineteenth and early twentieth century socialism, reform politics, and medicine. About two thirds of the correspondence was received by Blanchard Jerrold and by Adolphe and Alice Smith; letters to other recipients include several to Mrs. and Miss de Fonblanque.
Jerrold, Blanchard, 1826-1884
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1975 from William P. Wreden, on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTES
William Blanchard Jerrold (1826-1884) was the son of British playwright, journalist and political satirist Douglas William Jerrold (1803-1857). The elder Jerrold was editor of a number of publications including the Daily News, Jerrold's Shilling Magazine, and Lloyd's Weekly, as well as a regular contributor to Punch. Blanchard Jerrold also wrote frequently for these papers, and at his father's death he took over the editorship of Lloyd's. He was a prolific writer, a novelist and playwright as well as a journalist, and he shared his father's interest in social reform and the labor movement. His 1872 collaboration with the illustrator Gustave Doré, London: a Pilgrimage, contrasts the lives of London's rich and poor. Among his many other works are biographies of Doré, George Cruikshank, and Napoleon III, and a series of writings on food entitled "Knife and Fork." (More detailed biographies of both Douglas and Blanchard Jerrold may be found in the Dictionary of National Biography .)
Adolphe Smith (1846-1925) was a British journalist and socialist. He was born at Headingley, Yorkshire, but at least one of his parents was French; he seems to have lived in France for part of his life, and fought in the Paris Commune uprising of 1870-71. He wrote frequently on contemporary public health issues, such as the cholera epidemics in France in the 1880s and the spread of smallpox in London. He served as an interpreter at conferences of the International Association of Medical Press, and was the official Anglo-French Interpreter at Congresses of the [Socialist] International between 1882-1910. Smith is best known today for the text accompanying John Thomson's photographs in Street Life in London, published serially in 1877-78, which documents the life of London's poor; other full-length books include The Biography of Charles Bradlaugh and Monaco and Monte Carlo.
Alice Jerrold Smith (1848-1882), Blanchard Jerrold's daughter, married Adolphe Smith in 1872. She wrote A Cruise on the Acorn, a children's book published in 1875 by Marcus Ward & Co., as well as literary criticism for the Liverpool Courier.
Scope and Contents
The material in this collection appears to have been assembled principally for its autograph value. It was removed from an album shortly after its acquisition by the library; the original order of the material is not known. The collection includes letters and other items representing a wide range of prominent figures in nineteenth century British literature, theater, and art, as well as nineteenth and early twentieth century socialism and reform politics. About two thirds of the correspondence was received by Blanchard Jerrold and by Adolphe Smith and his wife Alice Smith; letters to other recipients include several to Mrs. and Miss de Fonblanque. In most cases there is only one letter or note from each correspondent.
The collection is organized into three series: Blanchard Jerrold Papers, Adolphe and Alice Smith Papers, and Third Party Letters and Other Manuscripts. All three are housed in one box.
Series I, Blanchard Jerrold Papers, is organized into two subseries: Letters to Blanchard Jerrold and Other Papers. The correspondence to Blanchard Jerrold is addressed both to him personally and to the Editor of Lloyd's Weekly. It includes letters from many of the leading figures in Victorian literary, artistic and theatrical circles. Letters from Clarkson Stanfield, Anthony Trollope, and John Forster concern a collection taken up by Jerrold for the actor Kenny Meadows in 1861. Several of the letters are addressed to Jerrold at the Reform Club, including one from William Gladstone. Also present are a letter to Douglas Jerrold and an autograph manuscript fragment of Blanchard Jerrold's The Life of Napoleon III.
Series II, Adolphe and Alice Smith Papers, is organized into three subseries: Letters to Adolphe Smith, Letters to Alice Smith, and Other Papers. The letters to Adolphe Smith document his involvement in the British and international socialist, communist, and trade unionist movements. His correspondents include prominent figures in the British labor movement, writers and activists in radical politics, Members of Parliament, and prominent international socialists and communists, as well as actors, artists, and physiologists. Letters to Alice Smith document her work as a literary critic for the Liverpool Courier. Most of her correspondents write to thank her for favorable reviews in that publication. Also present is the title page and flyleaf of an album (possibly the album from which the collection was removed), inscribed "Alice Adolphe Smith."
Series III, Third Party Letters and Other Manuscripts, consists chiefly of correspondence to various recipients from actors, writers, nobility, and others, but it also includes a small sketch of Thackeray, a manuscript poem fragment by Holloway, a manuscript titled "Extracts from Dr. Moore's Travels Thro Italy," and a list of names which may at one time have been represented in the autograph collection. A number of the letters are addressed to a Mrs and Miss de Fonblanque. A few of the letters were likely written to Jerrold or to Adolphe or Alice Smith, but have been included in this series rather than with their correspondence because the recipients cannot be conclusively identified.
Authors, English -- 19th century; Journalists -- Great Britain -- Correspondence; Socialism -- Europe; Theater -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Autographs (manuscripts); Jerrold, Blanchard, 1826-1884; Jerrold, Douglas, 1803-1857; Smith, Adolphe; Smith, Alice, fl. 1873-1881
- Blanchard Jerrold Papers, 1856-1878; Series I; .08'(30 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  Some letters in series III may also be to Blanchard Jerrold or his father, but were not included in this series because the recipient could not be conclusively identified.
  - LETTERS TO BLANCHARD JERROLD
    The letters are signed autograph letters unless noted otherwise.
    - Barr, Matthius, to the editor of Lloyd's Weekly, 18[73?] Sep 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bourbon, Auguste de, to the editor of Lloyd's Weekly, 1872 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Browning, Robert, regarding Francis Mahony, 1868 Jun 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Celeste, Madame, unsigned and written in third person, 1860 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dickens, Charles, 1868 Jul 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Doré, Gustave, 2 letters, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Forster, John, 1861 Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Gladstone, William E., written in the third person, 1868 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Hunt, Leigh, n.y. Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hunt, Thornton, 1861 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jeaffreson, John Cordy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Jerrold, Douglas, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Landseer, [Charles?], 1870 Nov 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - [Leighton?], P. H., [1870 Dec 20?] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lemon, Mark, 185[?] Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Lytton, Edward Bulwer, 1871 Aug 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Mathews, C. J., 1862 Feb 18 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Oxenford, John, 1873 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Panton, [Joseph?], 1862 Feb 10 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Reid, Mayne, 2 letters, one to BJ and one to "Dear Sir", 1875-78 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Smith, Albert, [1859 Aug] (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Stanfield, Clarkson, 1861 Jun 27 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Stanley, Arthur Penrhyn, 1871 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Tenniel, John, 1868 Jun 22 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Trollope, Anthony, 1861 Jun 21 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Wilson, Erasmus, 1858 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Yates, Edmund, 1861 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Jerrold, Blanchard, manuscript fragment of his The Life of Napoleon III, signed, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      "Book IX, Chapter IX. The First Year of the Empire"
    - Mackay, Charles, ALS to Douglas Jerrold, 1856 Feb 16 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Unidentified correspondent, ALS to Miss Jerrold (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Adolphe and Alice Smith Papers, 1872-1922; Series II; .13' (38 folders)
  Some letters in Series III may also be to Adolphe or Alice Smith, but were filed in that series because the recipient could not be conclusively identified.
  - LETTERS TO ADOLPHE SMITH
    The letters are signed autograph letters unless otherwise noted.
    - Aladin, Alexis, 1910 Sep 27 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Bradlaugh, Charles, two letters, 1873-80 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      With tickets to London Dialectical Society debate 1873 Jan 15, signed
    - Bunting, Sir Percy, 1910 Sep 1 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Cachin, Marcel, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Carrel, Alexis, 1912 Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Carson, Edward, typed postcard, signed, 1920 [Jun?] 1 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Cremer, W. Randal, 1906 [Sep?] 23 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Dilke, Sir Charles Wentworth, letter and note, 1880 Apr 6, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Grayson, Victor, 2 letters, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Herkomer, Hubert, invitation to "A. Smith and friends", engraved illustration, unsigned, n.y. [Mar 30] (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Herron, George S., 1911 Sep 6 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Irving, Henry, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Odger, George, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Richet, Charles, 1922 Dec 3 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Robertson, John M., 1910 Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Spargo, John, 1899 Oct 14 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      Includes copy of a letter from spiritual medium Thomas Robinson, who claims that the letter is written through him by the recently deceased Tom McCarthy.
    - Stokes, Rose Pastor, 1908 Sep 23 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Toole, John, 1874 Jan 13 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Tillett, Ben, 1889 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Webster, Benjamin, n.y. Aug 14 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Webb, Beatrice, 1907 Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Zetkin, Klara, 1904 [Feb?] 4 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Unidentified, 1872 Sep 26 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - LETTERS TO ALICE SMITH
    - Adams, W. Davenport, 1880 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Bradlaugh, Charles, 1873 Apr 24 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Brooks, Shirley, 1873 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Edwards, Amelia B., 1877 Aug 14 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Frome, Kate, 2 letters, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - McKinley, A. S., n.y. Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Maxwell, Mary Elizabeth Braddon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - [Mellow?], Charles, regarding Mrs Johnson's Bride Elect, 1879 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Middlemars, Jean, 4 letters, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Patterson, R. H., with salutation "My Dear Corisande", 1877 Jul 3 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Philp, Elizabeth, n.y. Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Regamey, F., 1877 Oct 27 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Thomson, James concerning his Vane's Story, 1881 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Collins, Mortimer, autograph poem "Fair Corisande," signed (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Title page and flyleaf of album, inscribed "Alice Adolphe Smith" (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Third Party Letters and Other Manuscripts, 1840-1928; Series III; .13' (34 folders)
  This series is arranged alphabetically by the name of the sender or subject. The items are signed autograph letters unless otherwise noted.
  - Anderson, Mary (Madame de Navarro) to Mrs Carr, 1902 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Aural Remedies Co., typed form letter signed H. H. Crippen, 1909 Nov 30 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Barnay, Ludwig, postcard to A. [T.?] de Fonblanque, London, 1881 Jul 19 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Begg, Isabella Burns, slip of paper autographed in the presence of Mr. Mayhew [?], Ayr, 1857 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Bombarda, Miguel, to "Mon cher confrère, 1906 Jan 17 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Buckstone, [John Baldwin?] to "Dear Madam", 1873 Nov 3 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Curtis, George William, to "Dear Sir" [George Pellew], typed letter, signed, 1888 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    Regarding Pellew's pamphlet Woman and the Commonwealth, or a Question of Expediency
  - Draper, Hubert, 2 letters to Mrs de Fonblanque, 1916-[17?] (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Faucit, Helen, to Mrs Hall, 1840 Jan 8 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - George [?], to Lady Jersey, 1859 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Hall, Anna Maria, to "My dear Lavinia", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Hall, S. [C.?] [Samuel Carter?], to Mr Edwards, [1878] May 27 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Hardinge, Lord, to Sir Edwin Landseer, envelope only (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - [Holloway], autograph poem "It is Xmas Eve..." fragment, unsigned, 1850 Dec 25 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Irving, Henry, to Miss [Lumley?], printed form letter regarding a coronation address to the King, 1901 Jul 18 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Leslie, Fred, to Miss [Sanitey?], 1889 Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Maspero, Gaston, to "Chère Madame", 1872 Sep 5 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Marchesi, Blanche, 9 letters and cards addressed to Madame de Fonblanque or simply "Dear Madame", 1916-28, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Mazzini, Giuseppe, to "Dear Sir," with calling card, n.y. Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Meadows, Kenny, autographed note stating the year of his birth, [1862] (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - "Extracts from Dr. Moore's Travels thro Italy," manuscript, mentions also Dupaty's Travels through Italy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Nieuwenhuis, F. Domela, to "Dear Comrade", 1892 Dec 20 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Phillips, Watts, to the editor of The Daily Telegraph [Thornton Hunt], 1866 Jul 5 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Price, [Mary?] to "Dear Lady," concerning "Not Forgotten League", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Salvini, Tommaso, to "Stimabilissima Signora", 1875 Jul 14 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Scott, Clement, to "My dear old Friend", 1902 Arp 21 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Sherrington, Jose, to Miss de Fonblanque, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Southey [?], carte de visite photograph of, in medieval costume, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Sydney, Lewis, 2 letters to Mrs de Fonblanque, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Thackeray, William Makepeace, pen and ink sketch by unidentified artist (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Thurston, Katherine Cecil, to Miss Hunt, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Wellington, Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of, to the Marchioness Wellesley, [1844?] May 31 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Whiting, R. to unidentified recipient, 1907 Jun 13 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - List of correspondents, on envelope (Box 1, Folder 102)
    Many of the names on this list are not present in the collection